Guide to the Baker family papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Baker family papers
1825-1832
MS 1704
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.25
(1 box)
The papers consist of letters exchanged by Oliver and Otis Baker, both graduates of Yale. Also included are letters to Otis Baker from his sister, Hannah Baker Lang, and letters to both Oliver and Otis Baker from others. A declamation by Oliver Baker is also part of the papers. There is reference to and some description of Yale life, interesting comments on being a teacher, and general comments on what life was like for a young man of the time.
Baker family
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Jonathan C. Brenner, 1995.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Oliver Baker, son of Samuel and Hannah (Bush) Baker of Bolton, Massachusetts, was baptized on September 27, 1801. While still an infant, the family moved to Templeton, Massachusetts. Oliver Baker graduated from Yale in 1829. He entered the Andover Theological Seminary in 1831, and a year later transferred to the Yale Divinity School. Oliver Baker died in Rahway, New Jersey on March 15, 1834.
Otis Baker, son of Samuel and Hannah (Bush) Baker, was born in Templeton, Massachusetts on September 27, 1803, and attended Phillips Exeter Academy. He graduated from Yale in 1831, and went south to teach. He died in Virginia in March, 1833.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of letters exchanged by Oliver and Otis Baker, both graduates of Yale. Also included are letters to Otis Baker from his sister, Hannah Baker Lang, and letters to both Oliver and Otis Baker from others. A declamation by Oliver Baker is also part of the papers. There is reference to and some description of Yale life, interesting comments on being a teacher, and general comments on what life was like for a young man of the time.
Teaching -- United States -- History -- 19th century; Durham (Conn.: Town) -- Description and travel; Methuen (Mass.) -- Description and travel; Teachers; Baker, Oliver, 1801-1834; Baker, Otis, 1803-1833; Yale University -- Student life
- Original accession
  - Correspondence
    - Baker, Oliver [incoming]
      - Baker, Otis, 1831-1832 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - Camp, Denis, 1831-1832 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - Camp, H. B., 1826 November 18 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Baker, Otis [incoming]
      - Baker, Hannah, 1827-1828 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - Baker, Oliver, 1825-1832 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Dearborn, [S.?] F., 1830 February 15 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Writings
    - Baker, Oliver [short treatise on the history of the temperance movement], undated (Box 1, Folder 7)